<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Henly at the visitation on the 27. of Aprill, 1626 Vpon those words of the 9. Psalme, vers. 16.</title>
            <author>Barnes, Robert, 1576 or 7-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04622</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1474</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114149</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849377</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849377</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14518</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04622)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14518)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 695:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Henly at the visitation on the 27. of Aprill, 1626 Vpon those words of the 9. Psalme, vers. 16.</title>
                  <author>Barnes, Robert, 1576 or 7-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. L[ichfield] and W. T[urner],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Rob. Barnes.</note>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14518:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14518:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT HENLY AT THE VISI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation on the 27. of Aprill, 1626.</p>
            <p>VPON THOSE WORDS OF the <hi>9.</hi> Pſalme, Verſ. <hi>16.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>The Lord is knowne to execute iudgement.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device(?) of head of woman wearing headdress</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. L.</hi> and <hi>W. T.</hi> 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14518:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14518:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL AND worthily diſpoſed Knight, Sir RICHARD BLVNT, High Sheriffe of Oxford-ſhire: Grace be multiplied in this world, and bleſſedneſſe in the world to come</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>VVorthie Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat hath beene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly offered to your religious <hi>Eare,</hi> is now within a few daies af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter preſented to your iudicious <hi>Eye;</hi> neither doubt I but as then it found attentiue audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with the one, ſo it will now finde kinde welcome and acceptance with the other.
<pb facs="tcp:14518:3"/> Only you will imagine what was then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered by voice can never bee carried ſo powerfully in papers as in ſpeech. <hi>Solet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptior eſſe ſermo vivus quàm ſcriptus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> the habit and geſture of a liuing man is the very life of Oratory. Yet will I not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of that good content a review may bring to a longing ſpirit. The words contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the two Tables which God gaue to <hi>Moſes</hi> from the holy mount were firſt ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the <hi>mouth</hi> of God ere they were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the <hi>finger</hi> of God, and then carried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the valley to be heard and kept of all the people. So may I likewiſe ſay of the Goſpel, voices and propheſies went of the blood of Chriſt ere ever it dropt out of his veines. But if gratious words had not fallen from the mouth of Chriſt, Chriſtians had neuer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived either the power or vertue of his death. For as there is a blood of <hi>redemption,</hi> ſo there is a word of <hi>reconciliation,</hi> and ſurely where the <hi>word</hi> teacheth not, there the <hi>blood</hi> droppeth not. You are religiouſly wiſe to conceaue whereat I aime: to wit, that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, preaching, and practiſing of pietie,
<pb facs="tcp:14518:3"/> may all goe together like <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Ionathan,</hi> of whom its ſaid, that they were louely in their liues, and at their deathes were not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided. I am ſure they are the beſt meanes to eſcape thoſe iudgements I came withall in that <hi>Viſitation</hi> diſcourſe. Which, I am made beleeue by many of my brethren &amp; thoſe of worth, ſo well relliſhed in the firſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, that I muſt not deny you a review. I was never ambitious herein, as well vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding mine own meanneſſe; nay my pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacie hath beene a ſecond happineſſe to me. But yet after the Cleargies dinner (whereof you were pleaſed to partake, and among the Lords Prophets, as before you had ſpent one houre in the <hi>Church,</hi> ſo you ioyed to ſpend another in the <hi>Chamber:</hi> a high argument of an intire zeale) ſo many importunities grew vpon me from ſome, tendering me their hands for the tranſcribing hereof from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, vndertaking you ſhould not faile in regard of that intereſt they might challenge in me, from all iointly ſoliciting for a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall favour, that at length I yeelded to ſend it aſſoone as a marriage ſolemnity was paſt
<pb facs="tcp:14518:4"/> in my pariſh, for the which I was to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided againſt the Sabboth following. Theſe inducements though powerfull, yet I will ingenuouſly confeſſe, were not my onely motiues. I haue heard &amp; alſo obſerued your vnfained affection to the truth, when as for it you haue in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner forſaken your owne, and followed S. <hi>Ieroms</hi> adviſe to <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> Honour thy father if he doe not ſeparate thee froth the true father. Otherwiſe, <hi>licet parvulus:</hi> and as he ſpeakes in another place to <hi>Heliodorus:</hi> Though thy little Nephewe ſhould hang vpon thy necke, though thy mother with her haire about her eares, and her garments rent, ſhould ſhew thee the breaſts wherewith ſhe nurſed thee, though thy father ſhould lye on the threſhold, tread vpon thy father to goe over, paſſe away with dry eyes to the banner of the croſſe. It is the chiefe point of piety to ſhew thy ſelfe cruell in ſuch a matter. Since I was taken out of that famous Nurſery, Magdalen College in Oxford by the liberall favour vnder Gods providence, of my Right Honourable good Lord and right zealous Patron, Viſcount
<pb facs="tcp:14518:4"/> Wallingford, together with his worthie Spouſe, my right noble Ladie, for the which the Lord of heaven multiply his bleſſings towards them; as alſo by a ſecond and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire reſpect of thoſe bleſſed ſervants of God M. <hi>Edmund Dunch</hi> and his religious daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in law, the Lady <hi>Mary Dunch,</hi> now both with the Lord, whoſe memories daily ſhine in their moſt hopefull heire, on whom Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God ſeemes, though in a farre diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent degree, to faſten that promiſe made to <hi>Abraham, Thou ſhalt be a bleſſing,</hi> Gen. 12.2. Since, I ſay, I was taken from the Vniverſitie and planted in theſe parts, I haue beheld faire buildings and ſweet ſeats both on our tops and vallies, but for matter of religion much averſeneſſe, or key-coldneſſe. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, the place of authoritie vnder his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie you now beare, ouerſwaied me not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for ſo much paines; which though, I here came not ſo welcome to you, yet I thank God from my heart, when I ſee men of your qualitie and condition ſelected for ſuch places; I am ſure then Religion ſhall ſuffer the leſſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14518:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I haue one boone to craue of you; which I earneſtly begge, and am confident in the obtaining, that ſince I haue beene drawne thus farre; what you haue in your hands you would by no meanes let it goe farther, nor to any other view but in your preſence. I am not ignorant how full of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation the times are, &amp; that queſtionings through miſinterpretation may occaſion much prejudice giue theſe papers leaue to ly by you as a pledge of my ſetled purpoſe to deſerue your loue in my readineſſe to beſtow my paines, if you ſhall requeſt them; and to be a continuall petitioner to the throne of grace that you may be kept by the power of God through faith to ſalvation In him I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my ſtudy at Greys <date>this <hi>4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                     </hi> of May, <hi>1626.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Worſhips aſſured <hi>ROB: BARNES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:14518:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PSALME: 9. v. 16.</bibl>
                  <p>The Lord is knowne to execute iudgement<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or By his iudgement he executeth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Princely Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> the ſweet ſinger of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael in this whole Pſalme celebrates Gods praiſes in reſpect of his mercies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the godly, &amp; judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the wicked, invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting others by his example to doe the like; and finally prayes for the proſperity of his ſervants, and ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his enemies. I intend no large paraphraſe on the whole, ſelecting this bare propoſition for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent occaſion, which brancheth it ſelfe into theſe foure particulars. 1. The Perſon, <hi>the Lord.</hi> 2. the attribute, <hi>Iudgement.</hi> 3. the commendation, <hi>executes:</hi> 4. the end, <hi>that we might know, and acknowledge him.</hi> The Lord is knowne to execute judgement. The Perſon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14518:6"/> is of an high elevation, and in his <hi>viſitation</hi> takes a full ſurvey of whatſoeuer paſſeth betweene heaven and ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th. <hi>Omnia aperta,</hi> all things are open to his view: <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4. The iudgement fearefull, <hi>for God is a conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire,</hi> and <hi>its a fearefull thing to fall into his hands.</hi> Heb. 10.31. The execution iuſt and free: for as he hath a viſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tation in grace and mercy, <hi>viſitavit &amp; red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> he hath viſited and redeemed his people: Luke. 1.68. and of pitty and compaſſion. <hi>Pure religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is to viſit the fatherles and widdowes:</hi> Iam. 1.27. So is there a viſitation with him in correction and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty. <hi>I will viſit their transgreſsions with the rod:</hi> Pſal. 89.22. and of wrath and fury, <hi>ſhall not I viſit for theſe things, ſaith the Lord? ſhall not my ſoule be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged of ſuch a nation?</hi> Ier. 5.29. Laſtly, the end is for reformation of all ſuch vnregenerate ones, who as yet remaine enemies to the croſſe of Chriſt, <hi>whoſe God is their belly, whoſe glory is their ſhame, who mind earthly things:</hi> Phil. 3.18.19. The perſon, attribute execution, end, are by the gratious aſſiſtance of Gods Spirit, and your (right worſhipfull, and the reſt deere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued) much deſired patience, at this time to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the ſubject of my enſuing meditations.</p>
            <p>And firſt of the <hi>Perſon,</hi> with whom I beginning e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven make an end, for I will not goe about to deſcribe either That he is, or What he is; the one is needeles, the other impoſſible. How ſhall I deſcribe him that dwells in a light that none attaines vnto? how ſhall I deſcribe him that hath made darkeneſſe his pavilion, meaſured the waters in his fiſt, <hi>ſits on the circle of the earth, in compariſon of whom the inhabitants are but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14518:6"/> as graſhoppers.</hi> Eſ. 40. How ſhall I deſcribe him that cannot be circumſcribed, who comprehends all things yet himſelfe not comprehended; is in all things, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe not included; moues all things, himſelfe not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; changeth all things, himſelfe vnchangeable. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, how ſhall I deſcribe him who is without quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty great, without quality good, without meaſure wiſe, without time everlaſting: in greatnes infinite, in vertue omnipotent, in wiſedome profound, in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell wounderfull, in judgement terrible, and in all ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues perfect and compleat. Search not then after the majeſty, leaſt thou be oppreſſed with the glory. There is, ſayes a learned father a holy kinde of <hi>ignorance</hi> not to ſearch after things vnrevealed, <hi>ſecret things belong to God, but revealed to vs:</hi> Deut. 29.29. As he is therefore in himſelfe I meddle not with him heere, but rather as he manifeſts himſelfe in his words and workes, in his mercy and iudgements, in his purity and power, theſe being the very hands with which he taketh hold of vs, and the armes he embraceth vs with, or ſtretcheth over vs. <hi>Bernard in his</hi> 8: <hi>ſer. Cant.</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribes theſe two hands to God, the one is <hi>latitudo quâ tribuit affluentèr,</hi> this is his bounty beſtowing his largeſſe, giving gifts to men; the other is, <hi>fortitudo qua defendit potenter,</hi> the hand of his power ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ouer all his creatures, to protect and defend them, and not ſo onely, but to puniſh them, when they ſhall offend him; to which purpoſe, <hi>&amp; Ierome de memb. Dei,</hi> ſaith, <hi>manus Dei flagellum,</hi> Gods hand is a ſcourge. With the one he ſeemes as ſtanding on mount <hi>Geraſim:</hi> Deut. 11.29. to deale abroad his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14518:7"/> 
               <hi>bleſsings,</hi> and like <hi>Homers Iupiter,</hi> out of one of thoſe tunnes and great veſſels which ſtands at the entrance of his pallace, ſets abroach his favoures to men: with the other as on mount <hi>Eball,</hi> he ſcatters his <hi>curſings,</hi> &amp; as out of the other tunne he drencheth men with affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, <hi>giving them plenty of teares to drinke:</hi> Pſal. 80.5.</p>
            <p>What I now ſpeake or might more enlarge herein reflects on vs (men, fathers, and brethren,) who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent this great perſon to our people, and hence are truely tearmed Perſons, embaſſadors for Chriſt. And ſecondly on you (deerely beloved) who are heere this day in the feare of God to preſent miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nures. This ſupereminent goodnes in the perſon calls to vs for imitation, that we would ſet copies of goodnes and ſanctity to our people, that our exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples may proue our beſt ſermons. <hi>Vita exemplaris, (ſaith Gregory in his paſtoralls) optima eſt concio, il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cum imperio docetur, quod priùs agitur quàm do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetur.</hi> A good life is the beſt ſermon, and he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with authority, whoſe practiſe goes before his preaching. For indeede it is a kinde of vnhappines as of princes ſo of prieſts, that <hi>quicquid faciunt praci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipere videntur.</hi> Neither can we be ignorant that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mole-hill in our miſbehauiours is a mountaine, euery moate in our eyes a beame. <hi>Chryſologus</hi> his tax in one kinde, <hi>Serm.</hi> 26. paſſeth popularly currant for all ſinnes. <hi>Ebrietas in alio crimen, in ſacerdote ſacrilegium; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter necat animam ſuam vino, alter ſpiritum ſanctitatis extinguit,</hi> I ſpare the engliſh. Herevpon ſo much cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouring hath beene about the cleargies exorbitancy.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14518:7"/> Our dayes are farre different from <hi>Conſtantines,</hi> who as <hi>Theodoret.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> of his ſtory, <hi>cap.</hi> 3. reports, when a libell or booke was given vp to him concerning ſome Biſhops miſdemeanures, firſt tied a thred about it then ſealed it with his ring, laſtly caſt it into the fire before all things were compoſed, profeſſing himſelfe would not reade a word in it, and ſaying if what was in it ſhould be divulged, the common people would grow more braſen faced in ſinning, gathering thereby a protection for their ſinnes; nay againe in the ſame chapter, when even he tooke a Biſhop committing any vncleane act, he would caſt his cloake ouer him, to keepe ſuch faults from the common eye. O the diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of times! But yet, I praiſe God, to his honour I may truely and boldly ſpeake it. If other places be anſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to theſe parts about vs, in reſpect of notorious crimes in the cleargy, I am aſſured much time might haue beene ſpared for <hi>reformation.</hi> In the meane time Antichriſt goes vp and downe the city, grinnes like a dog, and ſtriues to ſeduce our profeſſours with that groundleſſe poſition or principle. That firſt we muſt looke to the <hi>Perſon</hi> teaching, before we looke to the <hi>thing</hi> taught; thereby to bring in a ſeeming <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality</hi> to outface <hi>true doctrine.</hi> A poſition, I ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine without all ground. For firſt Chriſt hath taught vs what perſons ſoeuer they are that build vp his kingdome, they muſt goe on. Wherefore <hi>Iohn</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playning to him: <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.38 39. <hi>Maſter we ſaw one caſting out devills in thy name, who followed not vs. Ieſus faid, forbid him not, for whoſoever is not againſt vs is on our part.</hi> Secondly in the new Teſtament none
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14518:8"/> but enemies of the goſpell looke to perſons more then doctrine. The prieſts and elders ſaid to Chriſt, <hi>by what authority doeſt thou theſe things:</hi> Mat. 21.23. And the Synod at Ieruſalem asked <hi>Peter: by what power, and in what name haue yee done this:</hi> Act. 4.7. But of the true worſhippers of God we heare no ſuch thing. Which I ſpeake not as if ordinarily we ought not to aske after mens authority, this were the next way to leape from the ſhop-board to the pulpit with Browniſts, and other ſectaries; but to ſhew, <hi>doctrine</hi> muſt be preferred before <hi>perſons.</hi> Thirdly the <hi>Eunuch</hi> and <hi>Lydiae</hi> did not ill in hearing <hi>Phillip</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> without enquiry after their perſons, they knew that Chriſtians ſhould not giue an account at the laſt day of the perſons they heard, but of their obedience or diſobedience to their wholſome doctrine. Laſtly moſt glorious perſons may be full of deceit, they that come in ſheepes cloathing, may be inwardly rauening wolues, yea <hi>watchmen may be blind, and dumbe dogs that cannot barke:</hi> Eſ. 56.10. <hi>and greedy dogges that can never haue enough: from the prophets to the prieſts they may all deale falſely:</hi> Ier: 6.13. <hi>there may be a conſpiracy of them in the medſt of the Church:</hi> Ezek. 22.25. As in the Trent Councell. Yet thus farre I will hold with them, that the perſon doth much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the worke: the Apoſtle ſaid not in vaine. <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.3.14. <hi>Continue in the things which thou haſt learned knowing of whom thou haſt learned them:</hi> that is, God, yea and it may be, Me, Gods miniſter who haue bene in thy ſoule by the ſpirit of power effectually concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with my ſervice. Againe, it puts you in mind,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14518:8"/> the <hi>Church-wardens</hi> here aſſembled who as the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe of <hi>Cloe.,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.11. this day by ſolemne oath are to preſent that ſinnes may haue their iuſt cenſures. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber before whom you ſtand, whoſe oath you take, euen the oath of the Lord. <hi>Ex.</hi> 22.11. <hi>Non conſiderandum cui ſed per quem iuras,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ierome.</hi> Take heede then on the one ſide of <hi>ſpleene</hi> that you doe nothing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiouſly, ſo your <hi>accuſation</hi> may be iuſt, your <hi>affection</hi> vniuſt, and in doeing that, ye ſhall ſinne, which ye had ſinned in not doeing. <hi>Ille dat poenam, tu amiſiſti laudem</hi> he may be puniſhed, but thou ſhalt not be praiſed. On the other ſide of <hi>conniuence</hi> and <hi>partiality,</hi> for there is an <hi>Omnia benè,</hi> Latine too well knowne to the vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedſt, that ſwallowes vp all vanities. Drunkeneſſe, vncleanneſſe, ſwearing, profanation of the ſabbaoth, goe abroad all the yeare before, and when the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation comes, either the preſentment is packt vp with ſome recuſants names, or otherwiſe with an <hi>omnia benè,</hi> as if there were no recuſancy in good manners, this is not charity that couers ſinne, but a miſerable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence that cheriſheth ſinne. In the Creation there was an <hi>omnia benè,</hi> God reuiewed his workes, and they were exceeding good: <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. in our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there was an <hi>omnia benè.</hi> He hath done all things well, he hath made the blinde to ſea, the lame to goe: heere was an <hi>omnia benè</hi> indeed, but neuer any ſince. If any thing may vrge you to a ſincere diſcharge here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, me thinkes it ſhould be the conſideration of what followes in the next circumſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Iudgment.</label>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord is knowne to execute iudgment. <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14518:9"/> hoc iudicij, vtinam nemo tranſiret ſine iudicio:</hi> I will ſays one that no man would ſlight over this word Iudgment. In the Ciuill law the title <hi>de iudicio</hi> is a great title &amp; much ſtudied, but among Chriſtians it were to be wiſhed it were much more, that it ever reſownded in our eares, ariſe ye dead and come into iudgment. In the ſcripture this name is diverſly vſed. ſomtimes for <hi>wiſdome</hi> to diſcuſſe and diſcerne things doubtfull. <hi>Giue thy iudgments to the king.</hi> Pſal. 72.1. ſomtime for a <hi>moderation</hi> in puniſhing, <hi>Correct me O God yet in thy iudgment.</hi> Ier. 10. ſomtime it ſignifies the <hi>cauſe</hi> or <hi>controverſy</hi> to be iudged, occaſioning <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> to reproue the Elders of Iſraell becauſe the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes cauſe came not before them, they promoted it not, but put it off from day to day to gratifie their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſours. Somtime the <hi>word of God it ſelfe</hi> is called Iudgment 119 <hi>Pſal.</hi> either becauſe God in his word as a iudge pronounceth what he would haue done, or for that it containes nothing but what is iuſt, or that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſhalbe iudged, accquitted, condemned. So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>time the <hi>office</hi> of iudgment, &amp; publicke government. <hi>Deu.</hi> 1.16, Laſtly the <hi>puniſhment</hi> itſelfe, <hi>So ſhall thy iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t be.</hi> 1. kings. 20.40. <hi>the daughters of Sion ſhall reioyce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of thy iudgments.</hi> Pſal: 48.10. take it in what ſenſe you pleaſe either for <hi>wisdome</hi> to diſcerne, or <hi>modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to puniſh, or the <hi>cauſe</hi> it ſelfe, or the <hi>ſquare</hi> of iudgment, or the <hi>offices</hi> of iudging or puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſtill iudgment belongs to God; though I muſt confeſſe moſt properly and peculiarly in this place it implies <hi>Puniſhment</hi> the rather becauſe of the next word, <hi>exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes,</hi> hauing its due reference to iudgment. Many
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14518:9"/> are the ſinnes of a people, and therfore manifold are Gods puniſhments <hi>Ezek.</hi> in his 14. <hi>cap.</hi> from the 13. <hi>v.</hi> forward ſummes vp foure iudgments. Famine, Warre, Peſtilence, Evill beaſts. 1 <hi>Famine</hi> comes rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on a pale horſe killing with hunger and death, ſomtimes clad in a roabe of immoderate raine and ſhowers drowning the worlds plentie and the earths proviſion, ſomtimes bearing on her ſhoulder heavens of braſſe, and treading vnder her feete the earth of iron. <hi>Pale</hi> and <hi>leane</hi> ſhe is more then the picture of death, <hi>mors in illa</hi> as well as <hi>mors in olla,</hi> nay more, <hi>genus miſerabile Lethi.</hi> When God who giues to man the breath of life ſhall denie bread to maintaine life, when winter ſhalbe turned to ſummer, ſummer to winter, when a man ſhall riſe early and eate the bread of carefullneſſe and at night be to care for his bread, ſow much, bring in litle, the harueſt litle but the labourers many, when one plants another waters &amp; God denies the increaſe, is not this a great <hi>iudgment?</hi> Yea and a threefold ſin amongſt many haſtens it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> firſt ſwearing and forſwearing, that the very <hi>earth mournes becauſe of Oathes. Ier:</hi> 23.10. there was a famine in the daies of <hi>David,</hi> what is the cauſe? and they did break their oath. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.1. Do not men now ſlight an oath? is it not as common as words? yea a common accuſer ſays <hi>Auſtine</hi> is a common for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearer. Secondly the neglect of gods worſhip wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Iewes were ſo guiltie, and puniſhments brought on them for not repairing the temple. Now if the materiall temple and his ceremoniall ſervice cauſed ſuch diſpleaſure to ariſe what will the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14518:10"/> &amp; careleſſeneſſe of his reaſonable ſervice preſſe him to. The tribes went vp to the temple, it was Gods expreſſe commaund, the frequenting of the taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle. <hi>Exod:</hi> 23.17. So that publique meetings for his worſhip are not as ſome would haue it a Iewiſh ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie or ambulatory, to ceaſe with the law and that temple, but <hi>omninò perpetuum,</hi> altogether per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent in Chriſts Church; neither counts he himſelfe as well ſerued by ſitting in a chimney corner, though with devotion, as when we are praying and prayſing his holy name in the place allotted for his worſhip. A third ſinne is the waſting of Gods creatures, ſo that in reſpect of mens vnthankfullnes, and ſome lauiſhing of them, God takes them away. <hi>In quo quis peccat;</hi> Hee makes the puniſhment anſwerable to the offence. <hi>The drunkard ſhall be cloathed with ragges,</hi> Prov. 23.21. <hi>a louer of paſtime ſhall be poore,</hi> 21.17. the whore ſhall he bring to a morſell of bread. Secondly, <hi>war</hi> ruſheth forth, riding on a red horſe vnbridled, carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all things by force of armes, not lawes. A time wherein <hi>Pirrhus</hi> regards not the aged head of <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amus,</hi> nor yet the ſacred altar whereto he flies; a time wherein old <hi>Iacobs</hi> head is ſent with ſorrow to the graue, wherein <hi>Rabell</hi> weepes for her children, and will not be comforted, becauſe they are not; a time wherein either we muſt fight, and ſo run on a ſuddaine death; or flie, and ſo leade a tedious life. <hi>I haue taken away my peace from the people:</hi> Ier. 16.3. This our land hath often taſted of this miſery being ſome times ouer-runne with forreine enemies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide that great diſtraction betweene the two houſes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14518:10"/> of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter.</hi> In the compaſſe of which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, <hi>Comines</hi> the French hiſtorian in that large di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion touching the Engliſh warres <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 4. tells vs that ſeauen or eight battells were fought where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in died of the bloud royall threeſcore, or foureſcore Princes, &amp; himſelfe beheld a <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Exeter</hi> fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch miſery as that the ran after the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Burgun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> coach barefoote &amp; barelegged begging his bread for Gods ſake. I heard of a kind of a reſtraint within theſe few yeares &amp; yet ſcarcely know not the meaning, that preachers ſhould not amaze the people with fearefull preſages, of dangerous times to enſue, but O my ſoule, both ſecretly, and openly, pray thou that God in regard of the former ſinnes, may be pleaſed to auert this judgment. In the third place the <hi>peſtilence</hi> iſſues forth on a black horſe, killing with ſickneſſe and death, whoſe terrible blow among other places, wee in this towne and the borderers on either hand haue the laſt yeare felt, wherein one cries, O my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come not nigh me, for I am infected, another barr'd in by command, ſhut vp by ſickneſſe, nay worſe pend in by ſorrow, cryes out of a window, O my father, O my brother either now breathing their laſt or by this time dead. <hi>O bellum Dei contra homines.</hi> O the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of God that flies ſilently, ſwiftly, deadly: <hi>perniciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimè volat,</hi> ſaies <hi>Muſculus, exitialiter ferit.</hi> It ſpares none, neither the aged can be priviledged, though <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lib.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 50. auoucheth, <hi>Senes minimè ſentire peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentiam,</hi> that old men are neuer tainted with the plague; neither the coldeſt regions can ſtop the courſe of it. <hi>Poſſevinus de rebus Muſcouit, fol.</hi> 11. tells vs at
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14518:11"/> what time he was embaſſadour for the Pope in Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via, the plague which had ſcarce ever beene heard of before in that country <hi>ob intenſiſsima frigora,</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the extreame cold, yet it then killed many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands; hence is this arrow called alſo <hi>exterminium,</hi> a rooting out: The houſe may ſhield men and cattle from the haile, flight may ſaue from the ſword, ſoiour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in another country preſerue from famine, but in this contagion at home our houſes ſtifle vs, abroad the ayre infects vs. The Prophet in the fourth place comes in with the violence of <hi>evill beaſts.</hi> Indeed it is Gods goodneſſe that thoſe ſauage creatures flie into the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe from our company, whereas hee could ſend them into our peopled townes, and though in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues they are not ſo fruitfull, he permitting the milde to increaſe &amp; multiply, yet can he make them to grow into heards and flocks. You knowe how the Lord ſent Lions to teare the children of <hi>Bethel</hi> that mocked the Prophet. 2. <hi>Kings;</hi> and what fiery Serpents fell among the murmuring Iſraelites; and how grievouſly in the booke of <hi>Exodus</hi> the <hi>Egyptians</hi> with <hi>Pharaoh</hi> were op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with Lice, Frogges, Caterpillers. Plead no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity from theſe two laſt iudgements. If we avoid not and repent of the forenamed ſinnes, we ſhall all likewiſe periſh. The Prophet hath here ended his num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, but I haue not mine. One iudgement more is worthie our more ſerious meditation and preſent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, which God knowes is too much ſleighted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men as if it meerely came from man. It is an <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall iudgement,</hi> the fearefull ſentence of <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication.</hi> All the reſt eſpecially deſtroy the body,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14518:11"/> but this the ſoule. There are that draw this cenſure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from <hi>Adam</hi> whom the Lord caſt out of <hi>Eden,</hi> and ſet an Angell at the entrie of the garden, who by ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the blade of a gliſtering ſword feared him from reentring, not ſuffering him to taſt of that tree which was a <hi>Sacrament</hi> of life. The like doe the Hebrew in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters obſerue concerning <hi>Cain,</hi> whom the Lord caſt out and baniſhed from the face of God. For what elſe is his <hi>face</hi> but the place appointed for his <hi>worſhip,</hi> where he was wont to appeare to the fathers, &amp; where <hi>Adam</hi> and his ſonnes met together in ſacrifice to him. Come vnto the times vnder the law, how was this judgement tipified by the vncleanes keeping from the tabernacle, not entring the temple, not partaking of the ſacrifices, nor eating the paſſeouer. <hi>Numb.</hi> 19.13.20. and 9.13. Looke but into the new Teſtament, what meane the vſe of the <hi>keyes</hi> to open and ſhut, and the words of binding and looſing? Moreouer by example <hi>Abraham</hi> is commanded to caſt out the bond woman, with her ſonne out of his family which was the Church <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.10. <hi>Himinaeus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> concerning the faith made ſhipwrack, and are deliuered to <hi>Sathan</hi> that they may learne not to blaſpheme 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19.20. the Apoſtle commands the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to purge out the old leauen, that is, as is after expounded in plainer words, put away from yourſeleues that wicked perſon 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7.13. al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding to the paſſeouer which the Iſraelites were not to kill, till their houſes were rid of leauened bread. <hi>Ob.</hi> But this puniſhment and authority ſeemes needleſſe, for the ciuill magiſtrate is charged to puniſh ſuch as liue diſſolutely, he beares not the ſword in vaine. It
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14518:12"/> belongs to him to take away the life and limme ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the nature and quality of the offence, what place is there then for eccleſiaſticall cenſures. <hi>Sol.</hi> I anſwere, indeed there was a time when the eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall authority tooke vp in a manner all, and lay hard not onely on ordinary civill courts, but on <hi>Davids</hi> houſe, and the throne of kings: But <hi>God</hi> euer from the dayes of <hi>Lucifer</hi> gaue pride a fall, and pride of all ſinnes leaſt be ſeemes the Church; the time is now come that <hi>civill</hi> courts are as much too ſtrong (as in the beginning of this parliament, a reuerend <hi>Biſhop</hi> preached) and if they goe a little farther, I ſee not to what end our <hi>viſitations</hi> ſhould be kept. But to the purpoſe, both <hi>courts</hi> may well ſtand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the one hinders not the other. <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led this as a perpetuall order in the church. Mat. 18.17. <hi>If he ſhall neglect to heare thee, tell it the Church, if he neglect to heare the Church, let him be to thee as an heathen and a publican.</hi> Where our Saviour alluding to the cuſtome of the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> church, he ſhewes alſo that the <hi>Christian</hi> church can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not want this ſpirituall iuriſdiction. We are not to thinke, as ſome fondly imagine, that Chriſt pointed out the civill magiſtrate, when he ſaith, tell the Church; nor that thoſe words, (if he heare not the church, let him be to thee as a heathen or publican) intimate thus much, except he heare the magiſtrate of the ſame faith and religion with thee, thou maiſt goe to law with him, as if he were a heathen or publican, and haue him before a <hi>Roman</hi> magiſtrate, that is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane. For Chriſt ſpeakes not onely to the Iewes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14518:12"/> that then liued, but giues a remedy to be vſed at all times. The promiſe that followes, <hi>whatſoeuer yee ſhall binde on earth,</hi> belongs not to one time, one place, one people, nor to the civill magiſtrate, nor wrongs civill, but to the conſcience, and had beene impertinently added, if Chriſt had ſpoken of ſeeking civill remedy againſt civill wrongs, as may appeare by theſe reaſons. Firſt, the words concurring in the text touching binding and looſing, and elſe-where of opening and ſhutting, remitting and reteining ſinnes were neuer underſtood but of ſpirituall power. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the authority here ſpoken of, was ſuch as the diſciples preſent, ſhould ſometimes in perſon exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, but theſe exerciſed no civill power. Thirdly Chriſts words are <hi>imperatiue,</hi> Tell it the Church; not <hi>permiſsiue,</hi> you may tell. And Chriſt commandeth no man to perſecute his brother civilly, offending him before the civill magiſtrate; he commands to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue him, and to be ready to take another iniury, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then in law to purſue him: <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. Fourthly, the ground of this action is not ciuill, for then it ſhould more fitly haue beene named <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but here it hath the expreſſe name of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſinne. Likewiſe he teacheth a little before, of offences ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, and the cure of them; then he ſheweth our duty of ſeeking, and recouering euery brother going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray, by compariſon of ſeeking and recouering of a loſt ſheepe. So that we may conclude, that to take the word Church, for a company of civill magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, or a bench of Iuſtices hath no approbation of any author. But why doe I diſpute ſo long, I rather
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14518:13"/> com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o mourne and lament our peoples obſtinacie and improvidence, in ſleighting this puniſhment. Do yee know in what ſtate you are, while yee remaine <hi>excommunicated?</hi> I will tell you. <hi>Excommunication</hi> is a ſentence of the Church, whereby a member there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of convicted, or to be convicted of ſome greivous crime, as yet continuing vnrepentant, is driven out of the church, and out off from the communion and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhippe of the faithfull, that thereby he might be driven to repentance. O what a heape of miſcheifes riſe here vp together. I'ts <hi>bellua multorum capitum.</hi> Doth this judgement paſſe on thee? art thou excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated? firſt thou endeavoureſt as much as in thee lieth to blot thee out of Gods booke, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue thy ſelfe of Gods protection. Secondly, know that the ſentence pronounced by Gods faithfull mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter is ratified in heauen, Chriſt is the author of it. The <hi>Corinthians</hi> being charged to put out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them him that had offended, they muſt do it in the name, that is by the command of Chriſt. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4. Thirdly thou art barred from the word and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and prayers of the Church. The word doth the noe good, the ſacrament hurts, neither can we bleſſe thee in the name of god. Was not <hi>Nebuckud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezars</hi> caſe moſt fearfull when he was turned to feede on graſſe like an Oxe? but the <hi>excommunicates</hi> ſtate is worſe, he wants the food of eternall life. Fourthly thou art to be accounted as an heathen, now betwene the Iewes and heathens there was no commerce con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning gods worſhip. Fiftly thou being excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated out of one Church canſt not be admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14518:13"/> any other. Churches are ſiſters whom one receiues all receiue, whom one reiects all rerect. Were thou ſure ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auſtine Epiſt.</hi> 74. that thou leauing one ſervice thou ſhouldeſt betake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into no other, thou wouldeſt be carefull how thou diddſt forgoe it or off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end. Laſtly adde hereunto the decrees of princes &amp; and counſells, thou canſt haue no benefit of the lawes, others may ſue thee, but thou canſt not ſue others, others may make their laſt will and teſtament, but but thou maieſt not ſet thy houſe thus in order, others may challenge chriſtian buriall, but thou muſt be buried like an aſſe; as thou waſt out of the church through thy obſtinate life: ſo ſhalt thou not be brought neere it vpon thy death. As I would craue of you (right worſhipfull) to be ſparing in theſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions making vp an <hi>extremum fulmen</hi> againſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitents: ſo I cannot but iuſtifie your tenderneſſe herein vpon mine owne late experience you rather aiming at a ſubſtantiall reformation in the delinquents then any exactions. Howſoever the common con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit runnes riot as if all were for pay, I haue found the contrary from your vnderagents. Let that ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine as a tax in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> courts, which are more for payments then repentance, ſaying to their offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, diſcharge the court and be gone; and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, reforme and be readmitted into the Church. I remember i'ts noted of <hi>Irenaus,</hi> he earneſtly reproued <hi>Victor</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> for excommunicating many churches in <hi>Aſia,</hi> not for hereſy and apoſtacy, but for that they would not conſent with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in the celebration of <hi>Eaſter.</hi> I beſeech you let
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14518:14"/> not your excommunications paſſe for ſmall occurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces tending ſtill to reformation, and execution, which is my third circumſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <label>To execute:</label> God is knowne to execute. A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation that brings with it Gods glory, a lands bleſſing, and each particular <hi>peccants</hi> wellfare. <hi>The Lord ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cuteth iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe that are oppreſſed with wrong:</hi> Pſal. 103.6. The Lord hath executed his iudgement vpon Angels, cities, the old world; the great Monarchies, and mighty kingdomes haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of his iudgements, who as they ſpoyled others, ſo haue they beene ſpoyled themſelues: As we may ſee in the ſubuerſion of the Monarchies, ſpoken of by <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell,</hi> the <hi>Aſsirians, Perſians, Grecians,</hi> and laſtly <hi>Romans.</hi> His executions haue lighted on wicked kings, <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh, Saul, Ieroboam, Ahab, Zedechiah, Herod;</hi> vpon wicked prieſts, as thoſe of <hi>Baal,</hi> and <hi>Elyes</hi> ſonnes, vpon wicked perſons, <hi>Iudas, Achitophel, Abſalon, Corah, Dath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> and <hi>Abiram;</hi> in a word on wicked people that put the Sonne of God to death: <hi>Pilat</hi> that corrupt judge, who for f vour of the Iewes, and feare of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> condemned our innocent Saviour, was ſhortly after put out of his office, and retur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing to his houſe in a ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e content, made away himſelfe. <hi>Caiaphas</hi> was dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſed, and <hi>Ionathan</hi> tooke his roome. <hi>Herod</hi> that deſpiſed Chriſt was condemned by <hi>Caligula,</hi> to perpetuall baniſhment, where he died miſerably; and the other <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rod,</hi> who killed <hi>Iames,</hi> and impriſoned <hi>Peter,</hi> was eaten vp with wormes. As for the Iewes who cried, his blo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d be vpon vs and our children, they had their wiſh, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> any of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gues <hi>Ezekiel</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:14518:14"/> formerly mentioned, but overtooke them eſpecially want and famine. Through famine, as you largely heard from this place the laſt weeke, they were driuen to eate the leather of their ſhooes, girdles, bucklers, targets, the dung of their ſtables, and <hi>in fine</hi> their owne children. Wofull was this execution, as alſo that by warre, when the ſtreetes of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ran with bloud, when they were ſtill taken and crucified on croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and gibbets ſet vp before the walls, that they which were within, might ſee them, and giue over, but yet they would not; 500 a day were thus hanged vp, till there were neither trees to be gotten, whereon to make croſſes, nor any more ſpace leſt to ſet them vp in. Fearefull was the execution, when certaine of them getting meate from the enemies campe for compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſake were yet ſo purſued with Gods anger, that when they hoped their liues were in ſafety, ſuddaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the night, the bloody ſouldiers (imagining they had ſwallowed downe their gold and iewells for their owne vſes) ſlew them, ſlitting their bowels &amp; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in for that which was not there, to the number of 2000 in one night. What ſhould I ſpeake of thoſe cruell perſecutors, <hi>Nero, Domitian, Decius, Diocleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> with others? or of our home-papiſts, who periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Endor,</hi> and became as the dung of the earth; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo let thine enemies euer periſh, O Lord, who for thy goſpell and truthes ſake, vnrepentantly haue evill will at this our Sion. Thus execution paſſeth for Gods glory, yea and for the good of a whole kingdome too. <hi>Iuſtice exalts a nation,</hi> ſaith the wiſe <hi>Salomon:</hi> Pro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. For when ſin is ſome-way puniſhed, God
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14518:15"/> is pacified. Wherevpon <hi>Moyſes</hi> ſlew thoſe idolaters: <hi>Ex.</hi> 32.29. and <hi>Phineas</hi> executed iudgement, ſo the plague ceaſed; and <hi>Achan</hi> once ſtoned, the Iſraelites proſpered, and <hi>Ionas</hi> but caſt into the ſea, the waters calmed. Nay laſtly this execution tends to the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of offenders themſelues; better be here puniſhed then fall into Gods hands. It had beene good for <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes</hi> children that their father had firſt corrected them, not God. And I doubt not but theſe kinde of meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings returne many a prodigall into their fathers home. I ſpeake not this (right worſhipfull) as doubting your vprightneſſe, or to teach you that ye know not. For who knowes not that the law is the life of a kingdome, and execution the life of the law; when the ſword of <hi>Goliah</hi> is not lapt in a cloath behind the <hi>Ephod.</hi> For it is one of <hi>Machianels</hi> rules, how a conquerour might weaken a ſubdued kingdome, euen to lay the raines on euery ones necke; and to allow the people to liue euery one as he liſt in a lawles faſhion. Neither ſpeake I this to exaſperate your mind, aboue that, which nature &amp; the qualitie of offenders, and offences doth require. There muſt be a <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias. Elias</hi> was a fiery ſpirited prophet inflamed with zeale, <hi>Moſes</hi> of a meeke &amp; milde ſpirit. Both theſe tempers are a happy compoſition in a Viſiter, and make his breaſt like the ſacred Arke, wherein lay both <hi>Aarons</hi> rod and the golden pot of <hi>Manna,</hi> the <hi>rod</hi> of <hi>correction,</hi> and the <hi>manna</hi> of <hi>conſolation;</hi> the one a <hi>Corraſiue,</hi> the other a <hi>Cordiall.</hi> This ſpirituall <hi>Iuriſdiction</hi> ſhould haue both <hi>vbera</hi> and <hi>verbera,</hi> or be like the bees, hauing much hony, but not without a ſting. On<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14518:15"/> ſting be leaſt in deſire and intention, and the laſt in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, like God himſelfe, <hi>Qui habet in poteſtate vindictam, ſed mavult in vſu miſericordiam.</hi> The building of the church goeth ſlowly forward, though there be many labourers, yet there be more hinderers. God neuer had ſo many freinds as enemies. If the <hi>ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers</hi> looke not well to the buſineſſe, too many will make church worke of it, for ſuch loytering is falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into a proverbe. Men are fickle, as were the <hi>Galathians,</hi> and Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> if they be not often viſited, they will ſoone be corrupted. <hi>Luther</hi> ſayd in <hi>Wittenberg</hi> that a few fanaticall ſpirits had puld downe more in a ſhort time then all they could build againe in 20 yeares. Let but <hi>Moſes</hi> turne his back, and aſcend the mount to be Iſraels <hi>lieger</hi> with God, the people pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſpeake of making a calfe; he is no ſooner vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of out their ſight, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of mind, &amp; they fall to ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry. Our churches are not like <hi>Iriſh</hi> timber, if they be not continually ſwept there will be <hi>ſpiders</hi> &amp; <hi>cobwebs.</hi> I cannot but name one amongſt many; The deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in our Churches vpon <hi>Saints</hi> dayes and holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, a very plague that infects theſe <hi>chiltren</hi> parts. For you ſhall haue more attending the <hi>Cart</hi> in the lanes or the <hi>plough</hi> in the field, then accompanying the <hi>Parſon</hi> and his <hi>Clarke</hi> in the Church; we may iuſtly complaine, <hi>Religio peperit diuitias, filia devorauit matrem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> we are all for <hi>wealth</hi> but little for <hi>devotion.</hi> Our forfathers and fathers in their godly diſcretion allotted <hi>Eeves</hi> as well as <hi>Sundayes</hi> and <hi>holy</hi> dayes for ſurceaſing of worke, but now it is well if all the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both</hi> may go free for ſpirituall imployment. Oh the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14518:16"/> greedineſſe of our times; which formerly was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne. Beginne with the firſt time while <hi>Moyſes</hi> liu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and you ſhall find theſe feſtiuities whether <hi>maiores</hi> or <hi>minores,</hi> higher or lower yet they were <hi>vacativae ab opere. Buccinate,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> 81, 3. <hi>Pſal: blow vp the trumpett in the new moone, even in the time appointed, and vpon our ſolemne feaſt day.</hi> And it ſeemes theſe dayes were thus ſolemned, vſed as free from ordinary working in <hi>Elizeus</hi> time to whom 2. <hi>Kings</hi> 4. the <hi>Shunamite</hi> woman went for her dead ſon, thereby occaſioning her huſband to queſtion her <hi>quam ob cauſam vadis ad eum hodie, non ſunt Calendae, nec Sabbatha,</hi> why goeſt thou to him? this day is neither the Calends nor Sabboth, which argues they were freed from labour, becauſe her huſband inſinuated ſhe ſhould goe vpon a day, when he might be at leaſure from his buſineſſe, making in that reſpect a ſimilitude betweene the Calends and the Sabboth. Nay it was obſerued til the time of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auſtin de decem cordis cap:</hi> 3. For he by way of reproofe of the Iewiſh women, for another extreme of their overmuch daliancing on thoſe dayes, ſaith. <hi>Foeminae hebraeorum melius nerent, vel aliquid operis facerent, quàm in Neomenijs ſuis impudicè ſaltarent.</hi> The Hebrew women were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſpinne or doe any worke, then immodeſtly dance in their new moones. O when my eyes behold on an <hi>Easter Tueſday,</hi> or the like <hi>Feſtiualls,</hi> as they did on the laſt within halfe a mile of this towne ſome plowing. How doe I mourne, and wiſh that our right reverend <hi>Diocoeſans</hi> worthy ſermon preached in <hi>Oxford No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uem:</hi> 5. 1602. were now againe in theſe parts preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14518:16"/> who iuſtly gaue the reaſons why our Churches ſhould be frequented on ſuch times. One was for that we haue <hi>exemplum legis M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſaicae,</hi> the example of <hi>Moſes</hi> law, which is alleaged by them that are learned for one re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſon, why our <hi>Saviour Chriſt</hi> did inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te none though after, the Apoſtles themſelues in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and <hi>Austine,</hi> were thought to be the choiſe inſtitutors of moſt of them: then againe we haue <hi>rationem legis M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſaicae,</hi> the reaſon of <hi>Moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> law, to wit, a remembrance of Gods bleſſings. Thirdly the practiſe and authori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of Chriſts Church, ſince his comming. Fourthly the promiſe of Chriſt, If two or three are gathe ed together in my name, I will be in the midſt of them. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.4. how much more if the whole congregation were aſſembled, which with an army of prayers ſhould enforce his mercy. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you againe and againe take notice of this n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>glect, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay if it may be with your owne and your of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers eyes, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> referring this reformation to <hi>church-wardens,</hi> but that a more immediate execution, both vpon our <hi>gentry</hi> and <hi>inferiours,</hi> may bring God to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y knowne, and knowne in his <hi>Saints;</hi> and ſo I come to my laſt part, and end of all theſe executions in iudgement, that God may be knowne and acknowle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g'd. God is knowne.) <hi>Auſtin</hi> reades the words thus; <hi>Notus eſt Dominus propter iudicium quod fecit: Ierome</hi> thus, <hi>Agnitus eſt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus iudicium faciens:</hi> the vulgar thus, <hi>Cogn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcitur Dominus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ud c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ciens,</hi> and our laſt <hi>tranſlation</hi> thus, <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſe facit Iehovah iudicio quod exercuit;</hi> but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing one and the ſame thing, that the Lord God
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14518:17"/> hath, is, and will be knowne by executing iudgement. Two words ſhall diſpatch all, firſt a <hi>Quomodo,</hi> how; next a <hi>Quando,</hi> when. The <hi>Quomodo,</hi> how God is knowne, will appeare in the practiſe of a threefold du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For as one well ſaith, <hi>Iudicia Dei ſunt commendan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, formidanda, meditanda:</hi> Gods judgements firſt are to be praiſed and admired. The Lord is righteous in all his wayes, and holy in all his workes; they are to be prayſed in reſpect of their greatnes, ſtrangenes, goodnes. <hi>Abyſſus abyſſum inuocat. O the deepeneſſe of his wiſedome &amp; knowledge, how vnſearchable are his iudgements, and his waies paſt finding out:</hi> Rom. 11.33. We ſee the effect, not cauſes, the middle, not the end. <hi>David</hi> that numbred the people is ſpared, and the people numbred are deſtroied; the prophet ſeduced, is ſlaine by a lion, and the lying prophet that ſeduced him eſcaped; a theefe is ſaved at the laſt gaſpe, and <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> an Apoſtle condemned; <hi>Caeſar</hi> that hath the worſt cauſe, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cceedes beſt; <hi>Pompey</hi> that hath the beſt cauſe, yet ſpeedes worſt; Gods enemies flouriſh and are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted, when his freinds mourne and weepe. One would thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke the word of God prevalent in beating downe enorm ties faſter then Sathan could raiſe them, ſo that where the goſpell abounded, ſinne ſhould not ſuperabound; and yet this glorious ſunne hath not diſpelled all thoſe foggs and miſts, which haue ſurged from hell. But if the ſun cauſe ſuch a ſtinke, i'ts a ſigne ſome dung-hill is nigh, let it reflect on a bed of roſes, there is all ſwee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes. Theſe preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents occaſion ſome to deſpaire of, others to deny Gods providence, but let vs alwaies ſay. Righteous art
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14518:17"/> thou, O Lord, and iuſt are thy iudgements. His iudgements are ſometimes ſecret, ſometimes mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, alwaies juſt. One while he puniſheth in this life, and in theſe like courts, leaſt there ſhould ſeeme to be no providence; others remaine vnpuniſhed, leaſt there ſhould be thought to be no enſuing iudgement. Secondly, Gods iudgements are to be feared. If men liſten not when he ſpeakes by his word, miniſters, mercies; certainely he will be knowne by his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> firſt askes in a kinde of ſcorne, <hi>quis eſt Dominus,</hi> but after vpon ſight of his judgements, then <hi>digitus Dei eſt hic,</hi> this is the very finger of God; and againe, <hi>The Lord is righteous, but I and my people are wicked:</hi> Ex: 9.27. The moſt wicked haue trembled at judgements. <hi>Baltaſhars</hi> countenance changed at the hand-writing in the wall, and <hi>Felix</hi> at <hi>Pauls</hi> preaching of righteouſnes, temperance, iudgement to come. But if they quake not, imputing all to blind chance and fortune, it ſhewes they haue an atheiſticall and irreligious heart, euen worſe then the devills, who as <hi>St. Iames</hi> ſaith, <hi>beleeue and tremble.</hi> Whereas the truely ſanctified with <hi>David,</hi> cry out one while, from my youth vp till now thy terrours haue I ſuffered with a troubled mind; another while as it is towards the end of the 119 <hi>Pſ. O let my ſoule liue, and it ſhall praiſe thee, and thy iudgements ſhall teach me.</hi> Now laſt of all, Gods iudgements are to be pondered by frequent meditation, which in mid'ſt of tribulation, yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts the deiected, ſtrengthens their faith, encreaſeth hope: <hi>I conſidered thine euerlaſting iudgements, and received comforts,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt.</hi> But out alas how
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14518:18"/> farre are we from this ſerious thought, how little vſe returne we to our ſoules by theſe occurrences. We haue beene ſmitten indeede, and the hills haue trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and our carcaſes haue beene torne and throwne to in the ſtreets; <hi>for all this Gods anger is not turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, but his hand is ſtretched out ſtill:</hi> Eſ. 5.25. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the reaſon of all is our ſleight paſſing by theſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, not ſo often ſeaſoning our retired'ſt thoughts, as there is juſt cauſe. The wofull occurrences of times haue but the ſame working in men, which a ſtone hath when it falls into the waters. Falling in it maketh a great noiſe, and ſtirrer the wates very much, one waue begets another for a good pretty ſpace, at laſt the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion growes weaker and weaker, and the water re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes to his former ſmoothnes: ſo we heare of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe fearefull accidents, at the firſt comming we are much moued, it runnes from man to man with much ſwiftnes, but on a ſuddaine when this firſt addreſſe is paſt, the matter dyes; we are as we were, and the iudgement leaues no impreſſion. God grant the laſt yeares plague for want of ſerious plunging our thoughts, hath not found vs this yeare, as proane to worke wickednes with greedines as before. And thus much of the <hi>Quomodo,</hi> how God is vſually knowne. The <hi>Quando</hi> remaines, the time when God thus manifeſts himſelfe. <hi>Hugo</hi> the <hi>Cardinall</hi> on this <hi>Pſalme,</hi> mentions a threefold day, Wherein God is knowne to man, the day of <hi>tribulation,</hi> of <hi>death,</hi> and the laſt <hi>iudgement.</hi> He is knowne to ſome for their ſalvation, wherevpon ſaith the wiſe man of the wiſe man, that he ſees the plague and auoides it, <hi>facile la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queos
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14518:18"/> euadit in terris qui habet oculos ſemper in coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis;</hi> ſaith the <hi>Gloſſe.</hi> But to others for their deſtruction, they fall as a bird in the ſnare, God then is knowne of his ſeruants here more priuately, but hereafter to the whole world more publiquely, <hi>Luther</hi> on this <hi>Pſ.</hi> alſo writes how the Lord is knowne two wayes. Firſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, by puniſhing the vngodly, and preſeruing the righteous. Secondly inwardly through the terrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of conſcience. Shall I abridge all into one ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mme? Iudges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e e haue their courts, and are knowne in them: ſo God hath three courts to be knowne by. 1. of <hi>ſeſsion.</hi> 2. of <hi>conſcience.</hi> 3. of the generall <hi>aſsize.</hi> This of <hi>ſeſsion</hi> is for <hi>penalties</hi> on our bodies, goods, good name, either in our ſelues or others. Though I will confeſſe, the end of his puniſhments in this kind is not only for ſinne, but as in the blindmans caſe <hi>that the glory of God alſo might be manifeſted. Ioh:</hi> 9. If here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in man chance to eſcape, and this court of outward penalties take ſuch little or no hold on him, yet in the ſecond place there will ariſe <hi>perplexities</hi> of conſcience. <hi>God</hi> is the iudge in this court, <hi>the conſcience the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> the <hi>Devill</hi> the accuſer, the <hi>law</hi> the triall, the <hi>deede</hi> the euidence, the <hi>perſon</hi> the priſoner. Tell me not of peaceablenes of moſt mens conſciences. They may be quiet, yet not good; as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Bernard</hi> diſtinguiſheth. And in this quietnes ſhe may be firſt <hi>caeca</hi> blind, the blind man ſwallowes many a fly, and the ignorant many a ſinne. Concupiſcence the roote of euill, <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paul</hi> thought to be no ſinne, while the ſcales of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance were vpon his eyes; and I am afraid too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dare not looke into the glaſſe of Gods holy word,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14518:19"/> leaſt the number of their ſinnes, and foulneſſe of their ſoules ſhould affright them. Secondly ſhe may be <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure,</hi> ſleepy, that can, and will not ſee, with whom ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n &amp; Sathan are in league for a time; <hi>ſed iſta tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litas tempeſtas erit,</hi> this calme will proue a ſtorme, as <hi>Ierome</hi> notes. The world, fleſh, and devill hath ſo lulled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſleepe that they neuer dreame of heaven, nor hell, dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, nor iudgement, the noiſe of carnall pleaſures &amp; the voice of worldly profits doth drowne the voice of conſcience in them as the drummes in the ſacrifice of <hi>Mol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch</hi> did the cry of infants. O ye <hi>Polypragmaticall</hi> men th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t haue <hi>whole Mines</hi> and <hi>Mints</hi> of buſineſſe in your p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tes, that you are not at leaſure once in a weeke, in a moneth, in a yeare, nay ſcarce in your whole life to parlye with your poore conſcience, think on this and remember that if once ſhe awake, <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gulum pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet,</hi> like a wild beaſt robbed of her whelps, ſhe will fly to the throate of thy roule, ſhe will affright thee with terrible dreames, ſuch as <hi>Polidore Virgill</hi> mentions that <hi>Richard</hi> the third had the night before <hi>Boſworthfield</hi> wherin he was ſlaine. He thought all the deuills in hell haled &amp; pulled him in moſt hideous and vgly ſhapes. <hi>Id credo non fuit ſomnium ſed conſcientia ſcelerum.</hi> that was no fained dreame (ſaith he) but a true torture of his conſcience preſaging a bloody day to himſelfe and his followers. Thirdly ſhe may be <hi>obdurata</hi> caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized, hauing no ſence and feeling of ſin. <hi>Grauiſsime tunc aegrotat qui ſe non ſentit aegrotare,</hi> that man is deſperately ſick that feeles not his ſickneſſe. But what of all this? what if through habit &amp; cuſtome of ſinning, all ſhame of face and remorſe of conſcience be taken
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14518:19"/> away? what if through all this the wicked hath no bands in his death? yet know the generall <hi>aſsize</hi> muſt be kept; and the day of retribution will come after all. For as God was <hi>omnipotent</hi> in creating the world, <hi>wiſe</hi> in preſeruing the world, <hi>mercifull</hi> in redeeming the world, ſo will he be moſt iuſt at the latter day in iudging the world; to the vtter confuſion of all derid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that ſay moſt fooliſhly, where is the promiſe of his coming? inſtead thereof then they ſhall ſay, verily there is a God that iudgeth the earth. He will the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcan and ſift out all that is in man. He will then diſcover if our wiſdome haue not bene craft, our ſeuerity rigour, our iuſtice cruelty, our gouerment tyranny: He will make it knowne whether our authority haue not bene oppreſſion; our zeale contention; our humbleneſſe baſeneſſe; our ſimpleneſſe folly; and our fervour in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion formall hypocriſie. Chriſt who was once brought to the barre when <hi>Caiphas, Pon. Pilate</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> ſat vpon the bench, ſhall in that laſt and great <hi>aſsize</hi> ſit on the bench and theſe miſcreants ſhall be brought to the barre, the godly now are in want and woe while the wicked in this life take their eaſe, but then the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhall be tormented, and the godly reſt in euerlaſting ioy and honour. Let vs pray therfore that we may all of vs know God by his mercies not by his iudgments, as a father not as a iudg, by his iudgments vpon others not vpon our ſelues. And that at the laſt day when he ſhall gather all nations into the valley of iudgment, ſeperating betweene the good and the bad, as the good ſheepheard doth betweene the ſheepe and the goats, and ſaying vnto the wicked, goe ye curſed into
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14518:20"/> hell fire &amp;c. we may then be of that bleſſed number whom he will place at his right hand, to whom he will ſay, <hi>Come yee bleſſed:</hi> &amp;c. To him be glory, and praiſe, and majeſtie, now and euermore aſcribed: <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <trailer>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device(?) of head of woman wearing headdress</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14518:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
